<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Durasov House</string>
    <string name="continuew">Continue</string>
    <string name="point0">Durasov House:\nfrom an estate to the university</string>
    <string name="point0_text">
Welcome to the Durasov House, an administrative building of the Higher School of Economics.
\n\nIn the next hour, you will explore its rich history.
\n\nThe Durasov House was built at the end of the 18th century by the nobleman Alexey Durasov and his wife Agrafena.
\n\nIt belonged to the Durasov family until 1825. Then for 14 years it was owned by Count Dmitriev-Mamonov.
\n\nIn 1839 the Practical Academy of Commercial Sciences was situated in the House of Durasov. The Academy was here until its liquidation after the revolution of 1917.
\n\nDuring the next 150 years the Durasov House was occupied by the Socialist Academy, the Higher Civil Engineering School and the Kuibyshev Military Academy of Engineering. The latter has been in the building for 74 years.
\n\nIn 2006, the Durasov House became an educational institution again: the former manor was transferred to the Higher School of Economics.
</string>
    <string name="point1">Atrium \n11 Pokrovsky Boulevard</string>
    <string name="point1_text">
We are in the atrium, which has been used for keeping horses. At first, at the end of the XVIII century, the buildings around us were one-storey. Afterwards, as it is easy to notice from the facade, they have been "growing".
\n\nRecent renovation of the Durasov House lasted until 2018, the building was completely restored, from the facades to the interior decoration.
\n\nThe restoration work has strictly followed the principle of historism, which means an endeavour to return the original appearance of the noble estate: the colour of the walls and the type of the windows. At the same time, where it has seemed appropriate, the signs of other eras have been left, including the Soviet heritage.
\n\nThe signs of Soviet era we will see later, and now an exception may be worth mentioning. Please, pay your attention to the bay window. In the years of the Moscow Practical Academy of Commercial Sciences, which always needed more space, a four-storey building was erected between the bay window and the opposite building. During last renovation the future of that building was under long discussion by experts. As a result, a difficult decision was made, the original appearance of the square was returned and the outbuilding was demolished.
\n\nGetting back to the end of XVIII century, you are invited to the one of the entrances of the estate.
</string>
    <string name="text_expand_button">Info</string>
    <string name="point2">Guest entrance \nDurasov House</string>
    <string name="point2_text">
The 18th and 19th century building plans clearly show that the two entrances to the estate were symmetrical. Today, they have different configurations, the second one being considerably smaller. However, it is difficult to say exactly when it has been changed.
\n\nThis is a large ceremonial entrance. The gate through which cars enter the courtyard is original and witnessed the War of 1812. It was used to recreate the gate in the second entrance during the restoration.
\n\nWe mentioned the War of 1812 intentionally. At that time, the estate was the headquarters of Vendemin, one of Napoleon\'s generals. According to unconfirmed information, Napoleon also visited this house.
\n\nAs for the 1812 fire, some sources say that the house was substantially damaged, while others say the opposite.
    </string>
    <string name="point3">Eight-columned rotunda</string>
    <string name="point3_text">
A rotunda is a circular building, in most cases surrounded by columns and with a dome on the roof. The first rotundas appeared in Ancient Greece and Rome, and this architectural form was used to build temples. These buildings were called "tholos".
\n\nLater, the Italian word rotunda (Latin rotondus) was used for the name of these buildings (from the Latin rotondus meaning round) and round churches became very common in Western Europe.
\n\nIn the heyday of the architecture of noble estates, rotundas were often used to form arbours and viewing platforms in park ensembles.
\n\nIn the Durasov House the rotunda served as a grand entrance for guests to enter the house. It appeared in the building not immediately, but as an extension of the first quarter of the 19th century, when it was decided to create a two-story hall on the first floor.
    </string>
    <string name="point4">Restoration &amp; 9 layers of paint</string>
    <string name="point4_text">
The colour of the walls in this room deserves a special mention. During the last restoration, nine coats of paint were found on the grand staircase, which had been applied to each other after numerous repairs to the building.  An ochre yellow, similar to the colour of the facade of the Durasov House, was the first in this "puff-pastry".
\n\nHow many times was the House of Durasov restored?
\n\nThe exact answer to that question is unknown. Over the 250 years of its existence the building has undergone several major and minor restorations adding various additions, changing decorative elements and repainting the walls. The facades were restored in the 1950s and 1990s, the interiors in the 1980s, in particular.
\n\nThe most recent restoration, which lasted from 2006 to 2018, was carried out according to the principle of historicism. The main aim was to restore the mansion to its original historical appearance. In some places, however, it was decided to leave traces of other eras. This is why, for example, in the former chambers of Mother Agafena Durasova, the columns of the noble period are flanked by Soviet stars.
    </string>
    <string name="point5">Сorridor \n1 Floor</string>
    <string name="point5_text">
What do we know about the owners of the Durasov House?
\n\nAlexei Durasov, the manor\'s first owner, belonged to a well-known noble family that traces its history to the late 15th century.
\n\nThe brightest pages of the social life of the estate are connected with the son of Alexei and Agafena, Nikolai Durasov. He had a reputation as a man who was not the most well-mannered, but he was prone to epatage. One such manifestation was the construction of a manor house in Lublino in the form of the Order of St Anne after he received the order of the same name. In addition - with a statue of St Anne on the roof.
\n\nIn addition to lavish dinners, Nikolai Durasov was fond of theatre. There was a theatre school on the estate in Lublino, which trained about a hundred serf actors. Durasov\'s serf theatre, along with the Sheremetevs\', was one of the most famous in Russia.
\n\nWhat were the serf theatres in Russia?
\n\nAt the beginning of the 19th century there were about 10 serf theatres in Russia, including the famous Sheremetev and Durasov theatres. Most theatres were located on Moscow estates: Nikitskaya, Lublin, Arkhangelskoye, Marfin, Olgov and Ivanovskoye.
\n\nSerf actors performed for the general public both to earn money for the owner (the owners themselves sometimes sat at the box-office), and for free to entertain guests, as in the case of the theatre of Nikolai Durasov.
\n\nThe actors were just as disenfranchised as other serfs: it was not unusual for the owners to brutally punish them for mistakes onstage right backstage, and the audience could hear the sound of reprisals. The actors could also be returned to the rest of the serfs at any time, sent to hard labour, etc.
\n\nPositive changes in fortunes through performances in the theatre only occurred to a few of the hundreds of serfs. Perhaps the most striking rise up the social ladder was the serf actress Praskovya Zhemchugova, who became Countess Sheremetieva.
\n\nAfter the War of 1812, French prisoners of war began to appear in the landlords\' home plays. They acted in plays and sang in their native language, which delighted the secular public.

    </string>
    <string name="point6">Portico</string>
    <string name="point6_text">
The portico hall in the Durasov House is notable for several features. The first is the very large, not at all traditional niches - the remnants of that reconstruction of the early 19th century.
\n\nThe reconstruction involved the addition of a large two-story hall on the north side, to the left of the façade, and a new vestibule below. A third storey was added to the whole building and a new six-column portico was added to the main façade.
\n\nInterestingly, the portico was attached to the original building, as the researchers say, \"randomly\", without any connection with the internal capital walls. It is a good example of a classicist portico.
\n\nAnother curious object in this room are columns, which at first sight seem to us wooden.  They were probably in the very last room of the ground floor, in the apartments of Agraphena Durasova. Initially these columns were decorated with artificial marble. Interestingly, the restorers retained the stars on the capitals of the columns as an indelible trace of the Soviet period of the building\'s life.

    </string>
    <string name="point7">Refectory</string>
    <string name="point7_text">
This room was used for preparing meals. The table was laid for many guests of Nicholas Durasov\'s balls, including Empress Maria Fiodorovna and Princess Dashkova. The hosts themselves practically never ate in this room.
    </string>
    <string name="point8">Stove system</string>
    <string name="point8_text">
Another artefact is an element of the stove system, preserved from the 19th century.  According to experts, the quality of the masonry is indicative of a very efficient heating system for the manor at that time.
\n\nThe Durasov House used the same method used in all palaces in Europe, where heating was not done indoors, but outside, so as not to annoy the owners and guests with the presence of servants.
    </string>
    <string name="point9">Back entrance</string>
    <string name="point9_text">
We are approaching to the second entrance of the Durasov estate. It was much smaller than the front gates.
\n\nThis is where the latrines used to be, and the right gates were used to drive in the gilders.
\n\nThe uneven floor is another evidence that the building has been rebuilt many times.
    </string>
    <string name="point10">Main Staircase</string>
    <string name="point10_text">
We are going to the first floor of the house. In the 19th century, the Main staircase was decorated with statues in niches in the wall. However, various sculptures were displayed here in different historical periods. The Soviet period, for example, left a legacy of plaster busts of proletariat leaders.
\n\n3D models of bas-reliefs of Peter the Great, Mikhail Kutuzov and Alexander Suvorov are available in augmented reality mode.

    </string>

    <string name="point11">Unusual staircase</string>
    <string name="point11_text">
The staircase between the first and second tier has a traditional wooden balcony. The staircase itself could hardly be called traditional. In the manor houses of that time, the staircase had three flights of stairs: the central staircase was divided into two. Nevertheless, the configuration of the building did not allow the staircase to be constructed in such a way.
\n\nToday, the grand staircase has regained its original appearance and is reconstructed in yellow stone.
\n\nSome effort was required to restore the original marble columns. Some of the balusters are authentic, others are copies of the originals.
    </string>
    <string name="point12">White Hall</string>
    <string name="point12_text">
In the time from the 19th up until the 21st century, White Hall’s role has changed several times.
\n\nThe main hall: it was here where Nikolay Durasov held luxurious balls. After robust dinner in the refectory, guests would be entertained by orchestras and the serf theater plays;
\n\nThe home cathedral of the Practical School of Commercial Sciences: the church first appeared in 1851 and was consecrated in honour of Alexander Nevsky. On the third floor, adjacent to the church, was an infirmary where patients could hear blessing through open windows.
\n\nThe Alexander Nevsky Cathedral was one of the most beautiful home churches in Moscow. After the Russian Revolution, this church was closed and the majority of its icons and decorations perished.
\n\nThe study hall: after the Russian Revolution, when the Durasov House was converted from one academic institution to another, this room was mainly used for study and instruction;
\n\nToday, the White Hall is the main hall for key meetings taking place at HSE University. This is the place where meetings of the rectorship and international conferences are held.

    </string>
    <string name="point13">Red Hall</string>
    <string name="point13_text">
In pre-Revolutionary times, this was the place for many leisurely aftermeal chats. However, starting from the middle of the 19th century and on into the 20th century, these spaces were used as classrooms. Owing to this, the interiors have sustained heavy damage. Here, under many layers of different types of paint, experts were able to uncover artificial marble. Relying on small components and fragments, the materials were restored by workshop specialists.
\n\nThe doors are also 19th-century originals. They served as the models to recreate the remaining doors for the building’s ceremonial enfilade.

    </string>
    <string name="point14">Green Hall</string>
    <string name="point14_text">
We are now in the ceremonial hall of the Durasov House. It is here that guests would dine, after watching theater performances in the White Hall. The walls feature the same artificial marble. Although not “real”, the marble was no less expensive than the real thing, since the client could have selected any colour.
\n\nThanks to the restoration of the interiors of the Green Hall, two fireplaces and two stoves with their original white glazed tiles can be seen. They have been reassembled based on the technologies used in the 18th and 19th centuries.
\n\nAnother interesting thing to consider here is the chandelier. It is patterned on the chandelier that previously illuminated the White Hall.

    </string>
    <string name="point15">Blue Hall</string>
    <string name="point15_text">
The Blue Hall is one of the several premises in the building draped in cold tones, and the final hall of the central enfilade.
Here the chimney of the period has been restored too, standing open with its original flap-door for heating.

A guest room was likely here in the 18th century. During the time when the Practical Academy of Commercial Sciences resided in the building, this area operated as a classroom.

    </string>
    <string name="point16">Yet another staircase</string>
    <string name="point16_text">
Before you, there’s a cast-iron stairwell, built in the middle of the 19th century. Up until 2008, it had never gone through reconstruction, and it’s not hard to guess that it was in poor shape.
\n\nTo restore it, it had to be disassembled and then reassembled anew.
\n\nSuch staircases can still be found in several historical buildings in Moscow, including the Kremlin.

    </string>
    <string name="point17">Wing </string>
    <string name="point17_text">
As in any nobleman’s mansion of the period, the Durasov House includes a “black” entrance for servants. Its steps were initially made of wood and later replaced with stone. One interesting feature of this structure is its windows. During the building’s various reconstructions, they were reduced in stature significantly but today they have been restored to their original size.
    </string>
    <string name="point18">3rd floor</string>
    <string name="point18_text">
We are near the end of our excursion. For over 250 years, the Durasov House has been witness to the many dramatic events of Russian history. It is symbolic that today the building’s third floor offers a picturesque view of very different architectural monuments.
\n\nThere’s Troiskaya Church in Serebryanichesky Pereulok – a parish church that has been well known since the 17th century.
\n\nThere’s also the Shukhov Tower, which is a monument to the architecture of Soviet rationalism and one of Moscow landmarks. It is commonly associated with the technological breakthroughs of the 20th century, like radio communication and TV broadcasting.
\n\nThe tall building on Kotelnicheskaya Naberezhnaya is one of the so-called “seven sisters” – a striking example of the Stalinist Empire style. As per the general plan for the reconstruction of Moscow of 1935, it was supposed to be among the dominant buildings in the capital city. Today, however, it’s less imposing, but still very much recognizable and associated with the city’s many famous cultural figures. At various times, this skyscraper was home to the likes of the writer Konstantin Paustovsky, poets Andrey Voznesensky, Evgeny Yevtushenko and Robert Rozhdestvensky, ballet dancer Galina Ulanova, actress Faina Ranevskaya, writer Vasily Aksenov and many others.
\n\nAnd here, our excursion comes to its end.
\n\nThank you for your interest in the Durasov House and see you again at HSE University!
    </string>
    <string name="point_title">Point </string>

    <string name="exit">exit</string>
    <string name="poor_screen_resolution">Your screen resolution is too little. AR experience is not available for your device.</string>
    <string-array name="points_short_titles">
        <item>Durasov House</item>
        <item>Atrium</item>
        <item>Guest entrance</item>
        <item>Rotunda</item>
        <item>Restoration</item>
        <item>Corridor</item>
        <item>Portico</item>
        <item>Refectory</item>
        <item>Stove system</item>
        <item>Back entrance</item>
        <item>Unusual staircase</item>
        <item>Unusual staircase</item>
        <item>White Hall</item>
        <item>Red Hall</item>
        <item>Green Hall</item>
        <item>Blue Hall</item>
        <item>Yet another staircase</item>
        <item>Wing </item>
        <item>3rd floor</item>
    </string-array>

</resources>